in this problem
we must write a program that requests
two integers from the user and
adds them together and displays that
result
in this particular program we are going
to require that
one of the integers is positive and one
is negative
we're not going to direct the user when
we initially prompt them
to enter specifically a positive and
then specifically a negative integer
however once they have given both
integers
we want to check that one is positive
and one is negative
if not then we'll issue an error message
and prompt them again
we've been given a method called valid
number
and it will return a boolean if the
number is valid and
not equal to zero so if the user
inputs an invalid number then we will
display an error message and prompt them
again immediately
it's later that we'll check whether one
integer was positive
and one was negative
let's take this initial logic of
prompting the user for an integer
and checking whether it's valid and
extract it to a method
we can call this method read number
[Music]
and the first step is simply to prompt
the user
please enter a positive or negative
integer
we'll store the user input in a local
variable number
[Music]
let's pass number to our valid number
method
[Music]
and for now just output the return value
we need to invoke read number on line 11
of our program
[Music]
so we're prompted for a positive or
negative integer
if i input a valid integer that's not
zero
our valid number method returns true
if i enter 0 our valid number method
returns false
and the same if i enter let's say the g
character
so we should have a clear idea now of
how the valid number method is
validating that user input
now what we want to do if the user input
is invalid
is issue an error message and prompt
them again
if valid number returns true then we
want to go ahead
and return that number
will return an integer representation of
it so we'll go ahead and call string2i
on the user input now and
return that number as an integer from
this method
if valid number returns false when we
pass the
number variable to it then we want to
output
an error message and we'll let the user
know
that they can only input non-zero
integers
[Music]
and let's run the program one more time
just invoking this read number method
[Music]
so if i input a valid integer
no error message is issued
this time i'll enter zero and i see the
error message
invalid input that's great
however i want the program to prompt the
user again
so we want to issue the error message
and then prompt the user for their input
again
so we'll put this code in a loop
[Music]
and with this loop inside of a method we
don't need to use the reserve word break
here
because we have an explicit return on
line 9.
so if our number is valid we will
explicitly return out of the method
early
if it's not our loop will continue to
iterate
so just to see this in action
if i enter an invalid input
i see the error message and i'm prompted
again so we know that our loop continued
to iterate
this time i'll enter a valid integer and
you can see that we
return from the method
so this is a good start we are
validating whether the input
is a valid number now we need to
prompt the user like this twice and
verify whether
one input was positive and the other was
negative
so we can create a local variable first
number
and set it equal to the return value of
invoking our read number method
remember that our read number method
explicitly returns
the user input which will be a valid
number
converted to an integer so we'll
initialize first number
and second number and they will
reference the return value of
invoking read number the next thing to
think about
is how we can verify whether one of
these numbers is
greater than zero and one is less than
zero
and it doesn't matter which one is
positive and which one is negative
just that we have one of each
you could write this logic in several
different ways
but one easy way is to multiply these
numbers
by each other
[Music]
and if the product is less than zero you
know that you had one positive and one
negative integer
so if the first number multiplied by the
second number
is greater than zero we know that we
don't have
one positive and one negative integer so
we can
leverage this as part of an if statement
[Music]
if the product of the first number
multiplied by the second number is
greater than zero we want to issue an
error message
we'll tell the user sorry
one integer must be positive and one
must be negative
[Music]
now when i run my code if i enter
two negative numbers you'll see that i
get an error message
so this is correct however we want our
program to prompt us again
[Music]
this is another situation where we can
use a loop
[Music]
if we don't have one positive and one
negative integer
we will display the error message and
start over we will invoke the read
number method two more times
and reassign first number and second
number
will tell the user please start over
now currently we have an infinite loop
we don't have a break anywhere in this
loop
so rather than use an if statement in
this manner
[Music]
we can tell our program to break out of
our loop
if the first number multiplied by the
second number
is less than zero
and otherwise we'll output the error
message and continue looping
running our code again i'll input
two positive integers i see the error
message
and i'm prompted again
this time i'll enter a negative integer
and then a positive integer
and our program exits the loop
appropriately
[Music]
now there's one last step to this
problem which is to display the sum of
these two numbers
[Music]
i'll initialize a local variable sum on
line 22.
and add our two numbers together
[Music]
as you can see first number and second
number were
initialized on lines 15 and 16.
within the inner scope of the block
passed to this loop
so in order to be able to access first
number and second number
i need to initialize them in this outer
scope
i'll initialize them to nil initially
[Music]
and when our code executes lines 18 and
we'll reassign first number and second
number to the return value of our read
number method
so now we should be able to calculate
the sum without error
[Music]
let's output a nice message to the user
we could use string concatenation here
but we'll use string interpolation
[Music]
and let's run our program to see that
nice message to the user
i'll input positive 4
and negative 3
and our program displays the operation
and the sum
what's interesting about string
interpolation is
you can actually place any expression in
these curly braces so for example
[Music]
i could add first number and second
number right here as part of our string
interpolation
[Music]
i'll enter the same integers this time
and you can see that our code still runs
just as we would expect
[Music]
this look isn't quite as clean so
we'll stick with initializing our local
variable sum on 25 to calculate the sum